Guide to the Leonid Rzhevsky Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1948-1987; Series I; 5.84; (14 boxes)
  - YMCA-YWCA for Russians in Western Germany, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 294)
  - "Z" General, 1953-1981 (Box 14, Folder 295)
  - Zabezhinskii, Grigorii, 1953-1961 (Box 14, Folder 296)
  - Zaitsev, Boris, 1952-1971 (Box 14, Folder 297)
  - Zankevich, E., 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 298)
  - Zhigalova, Ol'ga
    See: Hauser, Ol'ga
  - _____, Lidiia Timofeevana and _____, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 299)
  - _____, Nikolai Vasil'evich, 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 300)
  - _____, Viktor Borisovich, 1954-1956 (Box 14, Folder 301)
  - _____, Vladimir Iaromirovich, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 302)
  - Unidentified incoming, 1949-1986 (Box 14, Folder 303-308)
  - Unidentified outgoing, 1953-1981 (Box 14, Folder 309-311)
- Writings and Lectures, 1941-1985; Series II
  Series II is organized into five subseries: Longer Works, Essays and Other Shorter Works, Lectures, Radio Scripts, and Writings of Others. Untitled and unidentified works are filed at the end of the alphabetical listing in each subseries. Newspaper clippings of printed essays are filed at the end of the Essays and Other Shorter Works subseries.
  Writings and Lectures consist of drafts and printed versions of essays, lectures, and radio scripts, and material relating to a few longer works (a playscript, Rzhevsky's dissertation and an edited volume of the correspondence of Kornei Chukovskii). The material chiefly documents Rzhevsky's literary analysis and there is little representation of Rzhevsky's many works of fiction.
  The subjects of Rzhevsky's literary analysis are diverse within the scope of Russian-language literature, ranging from Aleksandr Pushkin to Bella Akhmadulina. In his essays and lectures, Rzhevsky employed stylistic and lexical analysis to discuss creativity and the relationship of literature to society. He also addressed the importance of emigration in defining twentieth-century Russian-language literature.
  Some essays are written under the pseudonym L. Tann.
  Writings of Others consists of drafts of two essays in German by Maria de Smeth.
  - Longer works
    - Dvadtsat' dve neozhidannosti (playscript), draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 312)
    - "Rzhevsky Manual," draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 313)
      A collection of essays by various authors (including Rzhevsky) on stylistics.
    - Slovar' komedii "Gore ot uma" A.S. Griboedova, typescript, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 314)
      Rzhevsky's dissertation.
    - Tvorets i podvig ( Creator and heroic deed ), correspondence and notes, 1974-1976 (Box 15, Folder 315)
      About publication of the work and translation into English.
    - Zagadochnaia korrespondentka Korneia Chukovskogo, draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 316-317)
      A planned publication of the correspondence between Kornei Chukovskii (a Russian children's poet) and Sonia Gordon of New York City. The material consists of transcripts and photocopies of letters that date from 1964 to1967, annotated by Rzhevsky. Topics of the correspondence include Vladimir Nabokov, Nikolai Nekrasov, the exchange of books, and Chukovskii's health and personal life.
    - Untitled Russian-language reader for second-year college study, draft, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 318-319)
  - Essays and other shorter works
    Drafts and individual offprints are arranged alphabetically. Newspaper clippings of printed essays are arranged chronologically at the end of the subseries.
    Drafts (most are typescripts; a few are holograph) unless otherwise indicated.
    - "Aerztliche Hilfe", undated (Box 16, Folder 320)
    - "Devushka iz bunkera," abstract of novel, holograph draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 321)
    - "Dukhovnaia zhizn' v SSSR i polozhenie intelligentsii", undated (Box 16, Folder 322)
    - "Frau Pylesos", undated (Box 16, Folder 323)
    - "Iubilei Dostoevskogo v SSSR," printed version, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 324)
    - "Iz okon avtobusa", undated (Box 16, Folder 325)
    - "Khudozhestvennaia prosa 'novoi' emigratsii," printed version, undated (Box 16, Folder 326)
    - "K problemam sotsialisticheskogo realizma," notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 327)
    - "Die Kunst und der Totalitarismus", undated (Box 16, Folder 328)
    - "Malenkov v roli iskusstvoveda", undated (Box 16, Folder 329)
    - "Die medizinische Hilfe", undated (Box 16, Folder 330)
    - "Natasha perevodit vtorichno," notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 331)
    - "Ob odnoi tvorcheskoi preemstvennosti," printed version, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 332)
    - "Obraz rasskazchika v povesti Solzhenitsyna Odin Den' Ivana Denisovicha ," printed version, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 333)
    - "Otzyv na rabotu Dr. Vladimira Seduro", 1959 (Box 16, Folder 334)
    - "Pamiati G.I. Gasdanova," printed version, circa 1971 (Box 16, Folder 335)
    - "Pilate's sin: cryptography in Bulgakov's novel, The Master and Margarita," printed version, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 336)
      English translation of "Pilatov grekh"
    - "Poiski tvorcheskogo oazisa", undated (Box 16, Folder 337)
    - "Razgrom talanta", undated (Box 16, Folder 338)
    - "Retsenzia na rabotu stipendiata N. Bernera", undated (Box 16, Folder 339)
    - "Slovo i ego zvuchanie", undated (Box 16, Folder 340)
    - "Sluchai s zapevaloi," Russian original and German translation, undated (Box 16, Folder 341)
    - "Die sowjetische Literatur und der Realismus", undated (Box 16, Folder 342)
    - "Tupik v sovetskoi dramaturgii", undated (Box 16, Folder 343)
    - "Tvorcheskoe slovo i partiinyi zakaz", undated (Box 16, Folder 344)
    - "Tvorcheskoe slovo i propaganda idei", undated (Box 16, Folder 345)
    - "Tvorcheskoe slovo v emigratsii", undated (Box 16, Folder 346)
    - "Vladimir Maksimov na zapade", 1984 (Box 16, Folder 347)
    - Various authors, poetry, Russian translations by Rzhevsky, undated (Box 16, Folder 348)
    - Notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 349-350)
      Includes autobiographical notes.
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 16, Folder 351-352)
    - Newspaper clippings of printed essays, 1948-1985 (Box 16, Folder 353-360)
      Consist chiefly of critical essays printed in serial publications. Most clippings were published in Posev (1948-1953) and Novoe Russkoe Slovo (1967-1985) though there are also clippings from Deutsch-russische Stossrichtung (1953), Russkaia Mysl' (1957), and Literaturnyi Kur'er (1980s).
  - Lectures
    - "Aleksandr Blok (1880-1921)" lektsia chetvertaia, circa 1959 (Box 16, Folder 361)
    - "Bella Akhmadulina v semidesiatye gody", undated (Box 16, Folder 362)
    - "Chetvero", undated (Box 16, Folder 363)
    - "Glavnye cherty emigranstkoi literatury poslevoennogo vremeni", undated (Box 16, Folder 364)
    - "Interv'iu", 1975 (Box 16, Folder 365)
    - "K vecheru", undated (Box 17, Folder 366)
    - "Kornei Chukovskii - ob amerikanskikh pisateliakh", 1976 (Box 17, Folder 367)
    - "O sovremennoi sovetskoi poezii", undated (Box 17, Folder 368)
    - "O tainopisnom v sovetskoi literature", undated (Box 17, Folder 369)
    - "Pamiati Bunina", undated (Box 17, Folder 370)
    - "Pilatov grekh", 1968 (Box 17, Folder 371)
      For an English translation, see "Pilate's sin: cryptography in Bulgakov's novel, The Master and Margarita"
    - "Plemia", undated (Box 17, Folder 372)
    - "Poema A. Bloka Dvenadtsat' ", 1980 (Box 17, Folder 373)
    - "Rekviem Anny Akhmatovoi", undated (Box 17, Folder 374)
    - "Roman Gul' i ego Bakunin ", undated (Box 17, Folder 375)
    - "Russkaia emigrantskaia literatura posle vtoroi mirovoi voiny", 1971 (Box 17, Folder 376)
    - "Russkaia literatura v emigratsii: gody 1946-1970", undated (Box 17, Folder 377)
    - "Slovo o Esenine", 1975 (Box 17, Folder 378)
    - "Slovo o Marke Efimoviche Veinbaume", 1973 (Box 17, Folder 379)
    - "Slovo o Pushkine", 1974 (Box 17, Folder 380)
    - "Slovo o Zaitseve", 1973 (Box 17, Folder 381)
    - "Tema o neprekhodiashchem" (on the eightieth birthday of B.K. Zaitseva), undated (Box 17, Folder 382)
    - " Tikhii Don Sholokhova i problema avtorstva", 1974 (Box 17, Folder 383)
    - "Ulybchivye stroki Pushkina", 1974 (Box 17, Folder 384)
    - Untitled lecture on Vasilii Aksenov, undated (Box 17, Folder 385)
    - Untitled lecture on Vladimir Voinovich, late 1960's (Box 17, Folder 386)
    - Notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 387-388)
  - Radio scripts
    - Various titles and untitled, typescripts, undated (Box 17, Folder 389-390)
  - Writings of Others
    - "Landung in Muenchen" by Maria de Smeth, undated (Box 17, Folder 391)
    - "Das Schwein mit der Haube" by Maria de Smeth, undated (Box 17, Folder 392)
- Other Papers, 1961-1986; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged by type of material. Clippings about Rzhevsky are arranged chronologically.
  Other Papers include clippings about Rzhevsky, programs from conferences that he attended or organized, and receipts and other financial records. Conference programs include comprehensive lists of participants in symposia that Rzhevsky organized at Norwich University.
  - Clippings about Rzhevsky, 1950-1984 (Box 17, Folder 393-397)
    Consists of reviews, essays and opinion pieces on Rzhevsky's work, on other authors, and on related topics.
  - Clippings about Rzhevsky, 1980-1986 (Box 18, Folder 398-401)
    Includes Rzhevsky's 75th and 80th Jubilee and obituaries of Rzhevsky.
  - Conference programs, 1961-1985 (Box 18, Folder 402-404)
  - Financial papers, 1969-1980 (Box 18, Folder 405-407)
    Includes receipts for books, hotel stays and daily purchases and utility bills.
  - Medical papers, undated (Box 18, Folder 408)
    Consists of dietary recommendations. Does not include medical records.
  - Residential papers, 1970-1981 (Box 18, Folder 409)
    Includes newsletters from homeowners' associations.
- Oversize, 1.34; (1 box)
  - Rannit, Aleksis, 1966-1979 (Box 19, Folder 410)
  - Zagadochnaia korrespondentka Korneia Chukovskogo, draft, undated (Box 19, Folder 411)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.42; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Series I. Correspondence (Box 20, Folder 412-420)
  - Series II. Writings (Box 20, Folder 421-432)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize
  - Series III. Other Papers, Box 17 (Box 21, Folder 433-437)
  - Series III. Other Papers, Box 18 (Box 21, Folder 438-439)